{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "This man's opinion in Barron v. Baltimore refused to apply Bill of Rights protections to state\ngovernments. He was the target of Andrew Jackson's derisive remark \"now let him enforce it,\"\nand he asserted his Court's power in a case about \"midnight appointments.\" For 10 points, name\nthis Chief Justice whose ruling in Marbury v. Madison asserted the power of judicial review.",
      "answer": [
        "John Marshall",
        "Marshall"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Pope Leo I convinced Attila the Hun not to perform this kind of action. This kind of action\nwas done by Gauls following the 390 BC Battle of the Allia. In 410 AD, Alaric led an army of\nVisigoths in performing this action, which St. Jerome identified as the effective end of the\nEmpire. For 10 points, identify this action in which the \"eternal city\" is pillaged.",
      "answer": "sack of Rome"
    },
    {
      "question": "The formation of this institution triggered the Key West Agreement on its proper usage, which\nwas negotiated on its behalf by its first secretary, Stuart Symington. This organization conducted\nProject Blue Book, a study of UFOs, and it operates Area 51. For 10 points, name this branch of\nthe US military which operates B-52s, F-16s, and other fighter jets.",
      "answer": [
        "United States Air Force",
        "Air Force",
        "USAF"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1970, the concluding game of this event featured the dramatic entrance of an injured Willis\nReed. This event included the \"flu game\" in 1997 and an upset in 2011 that put a championship\nin the hands of Jason Terry, Shawn Marion, and Dirk Nowitski. For 10 points, name this annual\nJune event, which awards the Larry O'Brien trophy to teams such as the Bulls, Heat, or Lakers.",
      "answer": "the NBA Finals"
    },
    {
      "question": "This country's banks, which had been largely taken over by Russian organized criminals by\n2013, underwent a savings account \"haircut.\" This country’s \"enosis\" (pr. ee-NOH-siss)\nmovement propelled Archbishop Makarios to power, sparking an invasion that still divides this\nisland. For 10 points, name this country with Greek and Turkish sectors on an island.",
      "answer": "Cyprus"
    },
    {
      "question": "This instrument was invented by a Belgian seeking a solution to the problem of clarinets\nraising their pitch when overblown. This instrument was played by Cannonball Adderley as well\nas the composer of Giant Steps, John Coltrane. For 10 points, name this classical and jazz\ninstrument which has alto and tenor varieties and is a woodwind made out of brass.",
      "answer": [
        "saxophone",
        "sax"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In 1985, this company sued Minolta over the distinctive crossed letters in its logo. This\ncompany is the descendent of Standard Oil of New Jersey, and it employed Joseph Hazelwood,\nwho was accused of being responsible for a 1989 disaster on Prince William Sound. For 10\npoints, name this company whose Valdez tanker caused a huge oil spill, eleven years before it\nmerged with Mobil.",
      "answer": [
        "Exxon",
        "Exxon Mobil Corporation"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "The first Church council named for this place endorsed ultramontanism and espoused the\ndoctrine of Papal infallibility. The second council named for this place introduced the vernacular\nmass and renounced anti-Semitism. For 10 points, identify this namesake of 1868 and 1962\nCatholic ecumenical councils, which is also the independent state where the Pope lives.",
      "answer": [
        "Vatican",
        "Vatican City"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "This man refused to continue working on the film The Golden Age after denouncing his\ncollaborator, Luis Buñuel, for \"communism and atheism,\" three years after he completed Un\nChien Andalou (pr. uh shee-EN on-da-LOO) For 10 points, name this Spanish surrealist who\npainted The Persistence of Memory, which shows several melting watches.",
      "answer": [
        "Salvador Dali",
        "Dali"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Nobility serving under this dynasty followed the \"Table of Ranks\" to determine bureaucratic\nadvancement. This royal house came to power after three different \"False Dmitris\" were\nsuppressed during the Time of Troubles. For 10 points, name this house founded by Mikhail I in\n1613, which remained in control of Russia until the twentieth century.",
      "answer": [
        "Romanov",
        "Romanov Dynasty"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "(TIEBREAKER BONUS EXAMPLE) Whose nomination as Walter Mondale's running mate in 1984 made her the first\nwoman to be a major-party U.S. Vice-Presidential candidate?",
      "answer": [
        "Geraldine Ferraro",
        "Ferraro"
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man's reforms were sabotaged when Qi (pr. CHEE) sent dancing girls and horses to\ndistract the Duke of Lu. This man advocated the \"reification (pr. RAY-iff-uh-CAY-shun) of\nnames\" and the \"five relationships.\" For 10 points, name this author of the \"Five Classics\" whose\nsayings, collected in the Analects, form the basis of a traditional Chinese ruling philosophy.",
        "answer": "Confucius"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Confucius lived during the Spring and Autumn period, in which what Chinese dynasty,\nnominally in power from 1046 to 256 BC, was in decline?",
        "answer": "Eastern Zhou, Zhou, Zhou Dynasty"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During this century, the Ottoman Empire's Tulip Period began with the Treaty of Passarowitz\n(pr. puh-SAH-roe-vits). At the end of this century, the White Lotus Rebellion broke out in\nChina. The Battle of Plassey and the Black Hole of Calcutta took place in this century. For 10\npoints, identify this century in which Britain took control of Canada after the French and Indian\nWar.",
        "answer": "18th, 18th century AD, 1700s"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Battle of Plassey weakened what Islamic dynasty that had ruled in India since\n1526, transferring effective control of most of India to the British East India Company?",
        "answer": "Mughal, Mughal Dynasty"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Alexander Neckham first described the European use of this object, which began in 1190 after\nit was invented in China. This object was used in conjunction with Portolan charts to double the\nVenetian trading season, which previously relied on clear skies for navigation. For 10 points,\nname this navigational device which uses the Earth's magnetic field to point north.",
        "answer": "compass"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "What other great navigational problem was solved by John Harrison with the invention\nof the \"Sea Clock\" in 1730, winning a namesake twenty-thousand pound prize?",
        "answer": "longitude, determining a ship's longitude"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Ford administration declared this phenomenon \"public enemy number one\" and circulated\nbuttons which encouraged Americans to \"whip\" this thing \"now.\" Paul Volcker was instructed by\nthe Reagan administration to get this thing under control at any cost to the unemployment rate.\nFor 10 points, identify this phenomenon of generally rising prices.",
        "answer": "inflation"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Paul Volcker was the chairman of what body, a position later held by Alan Greenspan?",
        "answer": "Federal Reserve, The Fed, Board of Governors, Board of Governors of the Federal Reserve System"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This state's Jackson County is where the Garden of Eden was located in Mormon belief. This\nstate was added to the U.S. as a slave state in exchange for Maine coming in as a free state, in its\nnamesake \"compromise.\" For 10 points, name this state that shares its name with the longest\nriver in the USA, which meets the Mississippi River here near the Gateway Arch in St. Louis.",
        "answer": "Missouri"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Missouri city of Independence was the start of what route, which settlers took to\nreach the Willamette Valley?",
        "answer": "Oregon Trail"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man first came to prominence by suppressing the 13 Vendémiaire (pr. VON-deem-yair)\nrebellion with what Thomas Carlyle called \"a whiff of grapeshot.\" He made his brothers Joseph\nand Jerome into the kings of Spain and Westphalia, respectively. For 10 points, name this \"First\nCounsel\" who was defeated by the Duke of Wellington at Waterloo.",
        "answer": "Napoleon Bonaparte, Napoleon, Napoleon I"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Napoleon was able to remove Austria and the Holy Roman Empire from the Third\nCoalition opposing him with what great 1805 victory in what is now the Czech Republic?",
        "answer": "Austerlitz, Battle of Austerlitz"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "A scandal leading up to this ballot question involved abusive Twitter messages sent to J.K.\nRowling. Alistair Darling appeared in an August 2014 debate on behalf of Better Together,\nwhich led the \"no\" campaign on this question. For 10 points, identify this September 2014 ballot\nquestion which sought to make Edinburgh the capital of a new sovereign country.",
        "answer": "Scottish independence, Scottish independence referendum"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Which largest Scottish city by population was one of the few areas where the majority\nof people voted for independence?",
        "answer": "Glasgow"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "Troops who carried out this action referred to it as “Blumenkrieg”, a term meaning \"war of\nflowers,\" because they were met by cheering crowds. Kurt Schuschnigg (pr. SHOOS-neg) was\nforced to resign to clear the way for this action, which began on March 11, 1938. For 10 points,\nidentify this forced incorporation of Austria into Nazi Germany.",
        "answer": "Anschluss"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Austria was forbidden from unifying with Germany by the Treaty of Saint-Germain\n(pr. sahn zhair-MON), which was signed at the end of what war?",
        "answer": "World War I, First World War, the Great War"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "FAMOUS GREEKS",
      "prompt": "What person or god from ancient Greece...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was the leader of the Olympian gods and was depicted in a famous statue at Olympia?",
          "answer": "Zeus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Ran naked through the streets of Syracuse shouting \"Eureka\" after discovering buoyancy?",
          "answer": "Archimedes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Led a cult which opposed eating beans and discovered a side length theorem for right\ntriangles?",
          "answer": "Pythagoras"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the \"gadfly of Athens\" whose Apology was recorded by Plato?",
          "answer": "Socrates"
        },
        {
          "question": "Offered a salt spring as a gift to Athens, which then chose Athena as its patron deity instead?",
          "answer": "Poseidon"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wrote the first book of history, The Persian Wars?",
          "answer": "Herodotus"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was called the \"tenth muse\" for her accomplishments as a female poet on Lesbos?",
          "answer": "Sappho"
        },
        {
          "question": "Gave a \"funeral oration\" on Athenian ideals during the Peloponnesian War?",
          "answer": "Pericles"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "MEDIEVAL EASTERN EUROPE",
      "prompt": "In the Middle Ages, who or what was the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Empire which, by the 1070s, was reduced to the area around Constantinople?",
          "answer": "Byzantine, Byzantine Empire, Eastern Roman Empire, Eastern Roman"
        },
        {
          "question": "Country first organized by the Piast Dynasty, which was later invaded by its neighbor\nGermany to start World War II?",
          "answer": "Poland"
        },
        {
          "question": "Muslim empire based in Turkey which conquered much of the region from 1308 to 1571?",
          "answer": "Ottoman, Ottoman Empire"
        },
        {
          "question": "Modern-day country where the Grand Duchy of Muscovy formed around the city of Moscow?",
          "answer": "Russia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Group which briefly overran Eastern Europe after defeating the Hungarians at Mohi in 1241?",
          "answer": "Mongol, Mongols"
        },
        {
          "question": "City where Vladimir the Great converted a namesake state to Christianity before it became the\nUkrainian capital?",
          "answer": "Kiev"
        },
        {
          "question": "Prince of Wallachia (pr. wah-LAY-kee-uh) whose practice of putting opposing soldiers on\nstakes inspired vampire legends?",
          "answer": "Vlad the Impaler, Vlad Dracula, Dracula, Vlad III, Vlad Tepes"
        },
        {
          "question": "Battle, which shares its name with a Balkan country that declared independence in 2008 from\nSerbia?",
          "answer": "Kosovo"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "HERBERT HOOVER",
      "prompt": "Name the person or event from the life or presidency of Hoover that was...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "The four-term New Deal architect who succeeded him",
          "answer": "Franklin Delano Roosevelt, F Roosevelt, FDR"
        },
        {
          "question": "The Chicago mob kingpin convicted of tax evasion",
          "answer": "Al Capone, Capone, Alphonse Gabriel Capone"
        },
        {
          "question": "His \"Silent\" predecessor in the White House",
          "answer": "Calvin Coolidge, Coolidge, John Calvin Coolidge"
        },
        {
          "question": "The East Asian language he spoke, along with more native speakers than any other language",
          "answer": "Chinese, Mandarin"
        },
        {
          "question": "The prestigious California university which he attended in its first year",
          "answer": "Stanford, Stanford University"
        },
        {
          "question": "The popular nickname for the stock market crash of October 29, 1929",
          "answer": "Black Tuesday"
        },
        {
          "question": "The disastrous 1930 tariff bill which worsened the Depression",
          "answer": "Smoot-Hawley Tariff, Smoot-Hawley, Hawley-Smoot, Hawley-Smoot Tariff"
        },
        {
          "question": "A group of World War I veterans who marched on Washington",
          "answer": "Bonus Army"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The use of this three word phrase ended a secret program by which Ryan Crocker coordinated the capture of Al-Qaeda operatives. This phrase originally ended with the word \"hatred\" when David Frum wrote it into a section of the (20 pts) ",
        "2002 State of the Union Address that argued for the overthrow of Saddam Hussein. (10 pts) ",
        "For 10 points, give this threeword phrase used by George W. Bush to describe Iraq, Iran, and North Korea by analogy to an earlier grouping of Germany, Italy, and Japan."
      ],
      "answer": "axis of evil"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A major book about these places was based heavily on the recollections of Georg Tenno. These places were initially described only in \"samizdat\" literature, whose (20 pts) ",
        "possession could get a person sent to these places, which were the subject of the (10 pts) ",
        "Kolyma Tales. For 10 points, name these places whose \"archipelago\" is the subject of a book by Alexander Solzhenitsyn, who also set One Day in the Life of Ivan Denisovich in one of these forced Soviet labor camps."
      ],
      "answer": "gulags"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) During this era, Josquin des Prez (pr. JOHS-kin day PRAY) made advances in polyphony (puh-LIFF-uh-nee), and Giovanni da Palestrina wrote the (20 pts) ",
        "Pope Marcellus Mass. This era's music came under fire at the Council of Trent and was succeeded by the (10 pts) ",
        "Baroque period. For 10 points, identify this period in Western musical history in which motets and masses were the dominant form of music, and which shares its name with a \"rebirth\" in literature and visual arts."
      ],
      "answer": "the Renaissance"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This substance was the subject of the \"Letter to Queen Victoria\" sent by Commissioner Lin, who burned chests full of it on the beach. This substance was mixed with alcohol to make the eighteenth-century medicine (20 pts) ",
        "\"laudanum\" and was consumed in namesake \"dens.\" The seizure of the Arrow sparked a second (10 pts) ",
        "war named for this substance. For 10 points, identify this narcotic whose first war ended when the Treaty of Nanking granted European concessions in China."
      ],
      "answer": "opium"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Herbert Fairbank first explained the potential for this system in 1939 after expanding the Pershing Map. This system was authorized by a 1956 law but not completed until 1992, at a cost of 114 (20 pts) ",
        "billion dollars. This system was championed by Dwight Eisenhower, who had seen the uses of the (10 pts) ",
        "Autobahn system while serving in Germany. For 10 points, identify this road network which includes even-numbered east-west routes and odd-numbered north-south routes."
      ],
      "answer": "Interstate, Interstate Highway System, interstate highways"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Russell S. Penniman found a cheaper way to make this product, which must be periodically rotated to avoid the pooling of its active component out of the (20 pts) ",
        "sawdust medium. This product reduced the danger of using black powder or unmodified (10 pts) ",
        "nitroglycerin, and led to its inventor being dubbed \"the merchant of death.\" For 10 points, identify this explosive with mining and military applications, which requires a blasting cap and was devised by Alfred Nobel."
      ],
      "answer": "dynamite"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Roger Ascham described the use of this weapon in the manual Toxophilus, and it survived in the British army until World War II, when Jack Churchill killed a Nazi soldier with one of them. These weapons were sometimes named for the (20 pts) ",
        "Welsh people who invented them and perfected their use, and they were used to great effect by the English at (10 pts) ",
        "Agincourt (pr. AA-jin-core). For 10 points, name this six-foot-tall archery weapon which replaced the crossbow."
      ],
      "answer": "longbow"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This city was aided by a 1946 enforcement of the Smoke Control Ordinance under David Lawrence. Factory workers in this city told of Joe Magerac and invented a method of cooking steak that produces a charred exterior and raw inside. This city was where (20 pts) ",
        "Pinkerton detectives were hired to break the Homestead strike by Henry Clay Frick and Andrew (10 pts) ",
        "Carnegie. For 10 points, name this former center of steel production, which is at the head of the Ohio River in Western Pennsylvania."
      ],
      "answer": "Pittsburgh"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) (TIEBREAKER EXAMPLE QUESTION) Because two million acres in this American state were set aside for veterans, the land became known as the \"Military Tract\" and towns there were named Pompey, Solon, and Scipio. This state's \"burned-over district\" was the center of the (20 pts) ",
        "Second Great Awakening, and its city of (10 pts) ",
        "Cooperstown became the home of the Baseball Hall of Fame due to an erroneous belief that the game was invented there. For 10 points, name this home of the Finger Lakes and Buffalo."
      ],
      "answer": "New York"
    }
  ]
}